Chas Nelson

PhD. MSci

Current Position

2018-current EPSRC Doctoral Prize Research Fellow, University of Glasgow, Glasgow, UK.

Building optical and neuronal simulations of the zebrafish retina to explore the possiblity of combining light sheet microscopy and graph theoretics to interrogate zebrafish retinal development.

Employment

2017–2018 Research Assistant in Microscopy and Optics, University of Glasgow, Glasgow, UK.

Combining real-time image processing with low phototoxicity microscopy to capture synchronised 3D images of the *in vivo*, beating zebrafish heart.

Education

2013–2017 **PhD in Computer Science**, *Durham University*, Durham, UK.

Mathematical Morphology for Quantification in Biological & Medical Image Analysis

2009-2013

Master of Science, Durham University, Durham, UK, First Class Honours.

Biology & Physics within the Natural Sciences Programme

PhD Thesis

Title Mathematical Morphology for Quantification in Biological & Medical Image Analysis

Supervisor Dr Boguslaw Obara

- Description o Developing, validating & disseminating image analysis & processing solutions
 - o Vessel enhancement based on morphological operations
 - o Automated and accurate nuclei detection in fluorescent micrographs
 - o Brain vasculature segmentation and aneurysm highlighting in MRA images

Masters Thesis

Title The Scratch Wound Assay: Scratching Away at Cancer with Image Analysis

Supervisor Prof. Chris Hutchison

Description o Developed a scratch wound assay analysis solution capable of tracking individual cells & of analysing wound area

Experiences

Research-related

2018–2019 Undergraduate Supervisor, School of Physics and Astronomy, University of Glasgow, UK.

- o Designed and supervised the undergraduate research projects of two students
- o Guided students through theory, experimental design, programming, research and reporting
- o Provided pastoral support for getting summer interships and applying for further study and jobs

- 2018 Vacation Scholarship Supervisor, School of Physics and Astronomy, University of Glasgow, UK.
 - Successfully applied for EPSRC funding to support an undergraduate student during a ten week summer research project
 - $\circ\,$ Designed a coherent research programme for the student and supervised them throughout the project
 - o Guided student through complex theory, experimental design, data analysis and presenting skills
- 2017 Conference Organiser, Glasgow Imaging Network, University Glasgow, UK.
 - o Organised a one-day conference to bring together life scientists, physicists and engineers working on the development or use of imaging technologies
 - \circ The conference was a great success with $23\,\%$ of attendees having established new collaborations due to the meeting
- 2016-2017 Undergraduate Supervisor, School of Engineering & Computing Sciences, Durham, UK.
 - o Designed and supervised the undergraduate research projects of three students
 - o The report of one of Frank Ryan was highly commened in the 2016 Undergraduate Awards
 - o Guided students through theory, experimental design, programming, research and reporting
 - o Provided pastoral support for getting summer interships and applying for further study and jobs
- 2015–2017 Founder Journal Club, School of Engineering & Computing Sciences, Durham University, UK.
 - $\circ\,$ Founded the Vision Journal Club to help postgraduates develop their critical analysis skills
 - o The club focuses on image processing, computer vision & visualisation papers
 - o Chaired the club, organising papers & leading discussions
- 2015–2017 Junior Seminars Chair, School of Engineering & Computing Sciences, Durham University, UK.
 - o Chaired the Computer Science Junior Seminar series of lectures
 - o Invited speakers & organised sessions across a range of areas of interest

Teaching

- 2018–2019 Python Computing Course, School of Physics and Astronomy, University of Glasgow, UK.
 - o Developed a new Python programming course for the level 2 Physics undergraduate module
 - o Designed new teaching materials within the Jupyter Notebooks framework
- 2017–2018 Polarisation Practical Lab Design, School of Physics and Astronomy, University of Glasgow, UK.
 - o Developed a new lab for the level 2 physics undergraduate module
 - o Whilst the practical focused on experimenting with polarisation it was developed with the development of key skills as a focus
- 2017–2019 Frontiers in Physics Lectures, School of Physics and Astronomy, University of Glasgow, UK.
 - o Lectured on Imaging the Developing Zebrafish Heart as part of level 1 undergraduate physics course.
- 2016–2017 **Bioimage Analysis Lectures**, School of Biological & Biomedical Sciences, Durham University, UK.
 - o Lectured on Bioimage Analysis as part of level 3/4 undergraduate course Biological Imaging
 - $\circ~$ Developed digital imaging & image analysis curriculum & content for multidisciplinary cohort
- 2015–2017 **Postgraduate CPD Series**, School of Engineering & Computing Sciences, Durham University, UK.
 - o Developed a curriculum of CPD topics, e.g. delivering a conference talk, for the PhD cohort
 - o Delivered a seminar on the wide range of visualisation a plotting tools available to students

Policy

- 2018 Transparency of Evidence, Sense about Science, UK.
 - o A Spot Check of Government Policy Proposals July 2016 to July 2017
 - o The spotcheck scored "94 government policies [...] to assess how transparent they were about the evidence behind the policy. "
 - o Contributed as a policy scorer of government policies
- 2018 Member of Policy Sub-Committee, Royal Society of Biology in Scotland, Scotland, UK.
 - o Actively involved in the policy work of the RSB in Scotland
 - o Contributed to and edited collated responses to calls for evidence
 - o Involved in developing a database of routes into life science careers in Scotland

- 2016 Strategy & Policy Intern, BBSRC, Swindon, UK.
 - o Part of the Exploiting New Ways of Working science strategy group
 - o Contributed to the BBSRC UK-wide direction & strategy for bioimaging and related technologies
 - o Produced the public BBSRC Review of Bioimaging report
 - o Developed quantitative & qualitative data analysis along with exciting visualisations
 - o Delivered findings at high-profile meetings, e.g. with members of BIS, the UK governmental department in charge of science research funding
- 2012 MURN Researcher, Matariki Undergraduate Research Network, Durham, UK.
 - o Established a global research plan into interdisciplinary science in teaching & research
 - o Produced an internal report for Durham University that has since been used for internal strategy
 - o Collaborated with a global team including researchers from Australia and New Zealand
 - o Undertook training in qualitative research & education research

Outreach

- 2019 **Speaker**, 7 Minute of Science, Glasgow, UK, Revolutions in Modern Light Microscopy.
- 2019 Speaker, Café Scientifique Cockermouth, Cockermouth, UK, Revolutions in Light Microscopy.
- 2019 Speaker, University of the Third Age, Glasgow, UK, Revolutions in Modern Light Microscopy.
- 2018 Speaker, Café Scientifique Glasgow, Glasgow, UK, Revolutions in Light Microscopy.
- 2018 **Speaker**, *Institute of Physics Scotland Public Lecture Series*, Glasgow, UK, Imaging the Developing Heart: Combining Computing and Optics to Image and Quantify a Highly Dynamic System.
- 2013 Co-Founder, Durham City Café Scientifique, Durham, UK.

Other Experiences and Responsibilities

- 2017-current Mental Health Awareness Events, School of Physics and Astronomy, University of Glasgow, UK.
 - o Organised school-wide events for Mental Health Awareness Week 2018 including a poster campaign, coffee morning and a panel discussion from Mental Health First Aiders
 - Organised school-wide events for World Mental Health Day 2018 including a coffee morning and mental health colloquium
 - 2015-2017 Trustee, Ustinov College Graduate Common Room, Durham, UK.
 - o Trustee of a registered charitable body (no. 1164865)
 - o Part of Durham's historic listed collegiate system
 - o Ensured charity carried out its purpose for the benefit of the college members
 - o Complied with charity law and The Charity Commission
 - o Ensured accountability of the charity and its executive board

Awards, Grants & Honours

- 2019 Royal Society of Biology Outreach and Engagement Grant (£500)
- 2018-current EPSRC Doctoral Prize Research Fellowship
 - Covers full salary with no research funds
 - 2018 Glasgow Imaging Network 1^{st} Prize Poster Award
 - 2018 Institute of Physics Early Career Researchers Fund (£300)
 - 2018 Honor Fell/Company of Biologists Travel Award (£500)
 - 2018 EPSRC Vacation Scholarship (£2,300)
 - Awarded funds to support an undergraduate student during a ten week summer project
 - 2016 Wolfson Research Institute Small Grants Award (£2,000)
 - 2015 1st prize Images of Technology @ Durham 2015
 - 2014–2017 Biophysical Sciences Institute Junior Fellowship
 - Awarded to researchers with significant experience in interdisciplinary life science research
 - 2013 EPSRC PhD Studentship (3.5 years; £19,126 per annum)
 - 2013 Institute for Advanced Computing Research Grant (£2,000)
 - 2013 Honor Fell/Company of Biologists Travel Award
 - Full registration and accommodation costs at the BSCB-BSDB Joint Spring Meeting 2013
 - 2012 Matariki Undergraduate Research Network Research Grant (£2,000)

Publications

Journal Articles

- 2019 Çiğdem Sazak, Carl J. Nelson & Boguslaw Obara. 'The multiscale bowler-hat transform for blood vessel enhancement in retinal images'. In: Pattern Recognition 88, pages 739–750. DOI: 10.1016/j.patcog.2018.10.011. arXiv: 1709.05097 [cs.CV].
 - Joint first author. A top five computer vision journal (IF 3.962).
- 2019 Jonathan M. Taylor, Carl J. Nelson, Finnius A. Bruton, Aryan K. Baghbadrani, Charlotte Buckley, Carl S. Tucker, John J. Mullins & Martin A. Denvir. 'Hybrid optical gating for long-term 3D time-lapse imaging of the beating embryonic zebrafish heart'. In: bioRxiv. DOI: 10.1101/526830. bioRxiv: 526830.
 - Submitted to Nature Methods (IF 26.919).
- 2017 Chris G. Willcocks, Philip T. G. Jackson, **Carl J. Nelson**, Amar V. Nasrulloh & Boguslaw Obara. 'Interactive GPU Active Contours for Segmenting Inhomogenous Objects'. In: *Journal of Real-Time Image Processing* (2017-12), pages 1–14. DOI: 10.1007/s11554-017-0740-1. DRO: 23575.
- 2017 Chris G. Willcocks, Philip T. G. Jackson, **Carl J. Nelson** & Boguslaw Obara. 'Extracting 3D Parametric Curves from 2D Images of Helical Objects'. In: *IEEE Transactions on Pattern Analysis and Machine Intelligence* 39.9 (2017-09), pages 1747–1769. DOI: 10.1109/TPAMI.2016.2613866. DRO: 19838.
 - Highest ranked computer vision journal (IF 9.455).
- 2014 Carl J. Nelson, Patrick Duckney, Timothy J. Hawkins, Michael J. Deeks, P. Philippe Laissue, Patrick J. Hussey & Boguslaw Obara. 'Blobs and curves: object-based colocalisation for plant cells'. In: Functional Plant Biology 42 (2014-09), pages 471–485. DOI: 10.1071/FP14047. DRO: 24373.

Peer-Review Conference Proceedings

- 2018 Shuaa S. Alharbi, Çiğdem Sazak, **Carl J. Nelson** & Boguslaw Obara. 'Curvilinear Structure Enhancement by Multiscale Top-Hat Tensor in 2D/3D Images'. In: *2018 IEEE International Conference on Bioinformatics and Biomedicine (BIBM)*. 2018-12, pages 814–822. DOI: 10.1109/BIBM.2018. 8621329. arXiv: 1809.08678 [cs.CV].
 - This proceeding was invited to be extended as a full journal article for Elsevier Methods. Note that computer science proceedings are blind peer-reviewed equivalently to journal articles.
- 2018 Çiğdem Sazak, Carl J. Nelson & Boguslaw Obara. 'The Multiscale Bowler-Hat Transform for Vessel Enhancement in 3D Biomedical Images'. In: *British Machine Vision Conference 2018*. 2018. arXiv: 1802.05097 [cs.CV].
 - A top five computer vision conference. Note that computer science proceedings are blind peer-reviewed equivalently to journal articles.
- 2015 Philip T. G. Jackson, **Carl J. Nelson**, Jens Schiefele & Boguslaw Obara. 'Runway detection in High Resolution remote sensing data'. In: *2015 9th International Symposium on Image and Signal Processing and Analysis (ISPA)*. Zagreb, Croatia, 2015-09, pages 170–175. DOI: 10.1109/ISPA. 2015.7306053. DRO: 16627.
 - Note that computer science proceedings are blind peer-reviewed equivalently to journal articles.
- 2014 Carl J. Nelson, Martin Dixon, Pierre Philippe Laissue & Boguslaw Obara. 'Speeding up active mesh segmentation by local termination of nodes'. In: Medical Image Understanding and Analysis. London, UK, 2014-07. DRO: 15588.
 - Note that computer science proceedings are blind peer-reviewed equivalently to journal articles. 'Speeding up active mesh segmentation by local termination of nodes'. In: *Medical Image Understanding and Analysis*. London, UK, 2014-07.

Oral & Poster Presentations

- 2018 Carl J. Nelson, Charlotte Buckley, John J. Mullins, Martin A. Denvir & Jonathan Taylor. 'Imaging the developing heart: synchronized time-lapse microscopy during developmental changes'. In: Three-Dimensional and Multidimensional Microscopy: Image Acquisition and Processing XXV. Volume 10499. 2018, pages 10499 10499 -6. DOI: 10.1117/12.2290191. arXiv: 1802.05663 [q-bio.T0].
 - Proceedings. Presented at SPIE Photonics West 2018 BIOS (San Fransiscio, USA).
- 2018 **Carl J. Nelson**, Vytautas Zickus, Charlotte Buckley, Finn Bruton, Aryan Baghbadrani, John J. Mullins, Martin A. Denvir & Jonathan Taylor. 'Hybrid Optical Gating Allows 4D Imaging and Quantification in the Developing Zebrafish Heart'. In: *Frontiers in Bioimaging*. 2018.
- 2018 **Carl J. Nelson**, Vytautas Zickus, Charlotte Buckley, Finn Bruton, Aryan Baghbadrani, John J. Mullins, Martin A. Denvir & Jonathan Taylor. 'Hybrid Optically-Gated Light Sheet Microscopy Allows Long-term Timelapse Imaging in the Developing Zebrafish Heart'. In: *10th Anniversary Light Sheet Fluorescence Microscopy Conference*. Poster. Oral presented by last author. 2018.
- 2016 Carl J. Nelson, Chris G. Willcocks, Philip T. G. Jackson, P. Philippe Laissue & Boguslaw Obara. 'Application of High-Speed Level Set Segmentation to Light Sheet Fluorescence Microscopy'. In: Light Sheet Fluorescence Microscopy Conference. Presented by Boguslaw Obara. Sheffield, UK, 2016-09.
- 2014 **Carl J. Nelson**, Martin Dixon, Pierre Philippe Laissue & Boguslaw Obara. 'Speeding up active mesh segmentation by local termination of nodes'. In: *Medical Image Understanding and Analysis*. London, UK, 2014-07.
- 2014 **Carl J. Nelson** & Boguslaw Obara. 'A Bioimage Informatics QVEST: Quick, Versatile and Easy Segmentation & Tracking System'. In: *Society for Experimental Biology (SEB) Manchester 2014*. SEB. Manchester, UK, 2014-07. DRO: 16647.
- 2013 **Carl J. Nelson**, Tim J. Hawkins, Michael J. Deeks, Martin W. Goldberg, Roy A. Quinlan, Patrick J. Hussey & Boguslaw Obara. 'TANGL: Bioimage Informatics Tools for Analysis of 3D/4D Network Geometries for Life Sciences'. In: *Actin 2013. In absentia*. 2013-12.

Professional Bodies

2018–current Member of the Sense about Science Voice of Young Science Network

2016-current Member of the Royal Society of Biology, MRSB

• Elected Ordinary Member of the Scotland Branch committee

2016-current Member of the Royal Microscopical Society

2016-current Associate Fellow of the Higher Education Academy

2011-current Member of Institute of Physics, MInstP

Online Presence

• https://www.chasnelson.co.uk • @chas_nelson_

Blog The Little Eye: O DizzyHound

chasnelson.co.uk/thelittleeye ORCID 0000-0002-4114-1710

chasnelson.co.uk/feed ResearcherID F-5524-2015

n ChasNelson1990 ResearchGate Chas_Nelson